so we have seen some relatively general
fault tolerance techniques now let's
look at the fault tolerance techniques
for memory and storage we could use dual
module redundancy or triple modular
redundancy for memory and storage but
they are considered to be overkill for
these devices we can get better
techniques that protect us from similar
problems so dual module redundancy and
triple modular redundancy are typically
used for the hardware that does the
computation which cannot be protected by
some of the less expensive techniques
that memory and storage can benefit from
and these techniques for memory and
storage
are called error detection or error
correction codes
so the idea is that we can store bits
with some extra information that allows
us to detect
and or correct one or more bits of error
depending on the code so we don't have
to store everything twice or everything
three times in order to achieve
detection or correction of a single
error so the simplest technique that is
often used for memory storage is parity
with parity we add one extra bit to the
data bits and that extra bit it can be
computed simply as an xor of all the
data bits
when we do have parity if a fault flips
any one of the bits including the parity
bit the parity bit will no longer match
the data by flipping one of the bits we
are changing the result of this xor
to be the opposite of what it previously
was so when we read the data and the
parity and we see that now the parity
does not match data we assume that there
has been a bit flip and that's how we
detect a single bit error the next level
of error detection and correction codes
is the so-called ecc which stands for
error correction code and a typical
example of this would be a type of code
called sec
dead codes or
single error correction and double error
detection code
so this code can detect any one bit flip
and actually fix it or if there are two
bit flips we will find out that that
happened but we can no longer fix it
using this code an example of where this
type of a code is used is in data
modules that have ecc this is how they
are protected so pretty much if there is
a single bit flip in such a module you
don't even notice everything functions
well if there are two errors
in the data that is protected by the
same code then we will get notified that
there's been an error but we cannot
actually continue operating normally
because actually we cannot correct the
error near state anymore hard drives use
even fancier codes such as the read
solomon codes that i'm not going to go
into here and these codes can detect and
correct multiple bit errors and they're
especially powerful when we have a
streak of flip bits which happens for
example when the head oscillates a
little bit and while the disc is
spinning it for a while just is too high
above the platter and misses some of the
bits
and then for hard drives in addition to
these error detection and correction
codes there is a family of techniques
called raid
that we will look at next